when you study chemistry there's a lot
of things that come up when you're
making measurements and will refer to it
being an intensive or an extensive
property or variable and what we mean by
these is we really mean it's a property
that changes with amount or it's a
property that's more intensive which
doesn't change with them out and right
there is really what your definitions
are any property that you can measure
that as you change the amount of
substance but that property doesn't
change with the amount is called
intensive a really great example of this
is temperature it's one of our premier
intensive variables if you will a great
example if you had a glass of water
that's 25 degrees C and you pour half
the water into another glass and ask
yourself now what's the temperature
temperature still 25 degrees because
it's an intensive property it absolutely
does not matter about the amount that
you have it's intensive now let's
compare that to the mass of the water if
I have a glass of water
I know it's mass is say 500 grams and I
pour half of it out now the mass is not
500 grams it's 250 grams that's because
that's an extensive variable extensive
properties vary with the amount and we
love to quantify amounts we quantify in
mass and grams we quantify ammount
itself in moles of substance we quantify
length how long is something how tall is
something volume is a great example of
an extensive property that actually
brings in length three times height
depth and width you multiply all three
of them you get yourself a volume which
is very extensive you get more amount
you get a bigger volume an interesting
thing though about extensive properties
if you ratio one extensive property
against another extensive property you
get an intensive property a great
example of this is density density is
mass per unit volume the mass is
extensive the more you
have the more mass you have volume is
extensive the more volume you have the
more the number goes up if you Rea show
them mass divided by volume you get
density and that's intensive the water
example I gave earlier when I pour it
doesn't matter when I split it the
density is still approximately one gram
per milliliter even in the part I pour
it off it's one gram per milliliter so
this is an important concept you will
see over and over when you're answering
problems numerically in a chemistry
class is the answer an intensive or is
it an extensive property one last thing
extensive properties by themselves tend
not to reveal much about what the
substance actually is for example let's
say I have a substance and I tell you
it's 500 grams that really tells you
nothing about the substance other than
the amount I have but if I tell you I
have a substance that has a density of
one gram per milliliter it really limits
you on your choices of what that could
be and so what we tend to do in the
sciences and what we do in chemistry is
we list intensive properties and if you
get a good listing of them it truly
identify that substance as being a
unique version of those intensive
properties meaning we like to
characterize matter by listing intensive
properties and that's really what the
importance of both of these things are
and you need to keep track of them